[Music]
hi everybody welcome back to the channel
today's video is vanilla
[Music]
i mean it's super boring
but lots of people have asked for it i
would never personally buy vanilla ice
cream in a store or a restaurant
or a shop you either a vanilla or a
chocolate that seems to be what people
say
regarding ice cream i'm definitely a
chocolate ice cream person
but
sometimes a vanilla ice cream just goes
really well with other foods like pies
and stuff like that you know not english
pies you know steak and kidney pie with
ice cream
no that's going too far
so
if you want to see how i make
custard-based vanilla ice cream stick
around and we'll show you
so to start this ice cream add in your
milk to your pan and just turn the heat
on nice and gently add in your sugar and
here we've added our dextrose which has
a stabilizer in it if you're going to
use that and the light brown sugar now
that light brown sugar just helps bring
the caramel elements of vanilla flavor
forward slightly
it will make it a little bit darker in
color but not too bad then add in your
egg yolks and again this is right at the
start the milk isn't even up to any kind
of temperature at the moment this is the
best way and safest way to make a
custard ice cream base
once it's all completely mixed in you
can actually start bringing the
temperature up
finally adding in your skimmed milk
powder
so once your base is up to temperature
again we've got egg yolks here so a lot
of people like to take up to 70 degrees
if you don't have a thermometer that is
the temperature where your ice cream
base will start to steam ever so
slightly no bubbles but you'll see steam
rising from your milk solution
at that stage turn off the heat and just
let it rest for a few minutes whilst
it's resting you can take your vanilla
pods now the vanilla pods i've used here
are really really skinny and there's not
a lot inside so i've actually used two
but if you've got really nice plump
vanilla pods just go for one
split the pods down the middle take the
seeds out and then put them in your
custard base
finally add in the actual pods
themselves and let it sit there just for
a couple of minutes to infuse before you
take it off the hob again when there's
no temperature there and put it in a
container to chill in the fridge
once your base is completely chilled
take it out the fridge give it one final
whisk just to make sure it's fully
emulsified and combined together and
then pour in your ice cream machine as
you would do normally
once it's ready take it out put it in a
tub and put it in the freezer for a good
few hours
and it's the next day as if
like magic we're gonna get some vanilla
ice cream scooped up into the bowl and
see how this one turned out
[Music]
and there we go
so couple of things to mention
i used two vanilla pods because they
were really really skinny and not a lot
inside there i did use vanilla pods in
another ice cream before from a
different supplier and they were really
really good big fat juicy plump vanilla
pods
probably three times the size of the
ones i got here these these are just
supermarket
i mean they're you know the
supermarket's luxury brand but
they're not luxury at all
so
if you
get your vanilla pods from somewhere you
know decent and they're a good size just
go with one you can
absolutely use vanilla extract i would
avoid vanilla essence that is not real
vanilla that's made using vanillin which
is a very different thing altogether
if you want to have a look at the
differences between the different types
of vanilla you can check out our history
of vanilla ice cream i'll put a link in
the description below
but now we're going to try this and see
what it turned out like
[Music]
i don't want to come across
unenthusiastic about vanilla ice cream
it is still i think the most popular
flavor of ice cream in the world
but i guess when you are in my position
you can make any ice cream you like
vanilla ends up taking a back seat but
my wife rightly pointed out that it is a
perfect base for other things
i probably wouldn't put this much
vanilla in it you know maybe vanilla
pods because that flavour can become
quite strong and overtake other flavors
but you could add a caramel swell to
this or brownie pieces or
you know fudge chunks you you could do
anything you like with this and you'd
end up with a really good ice cream and
interestingly
ben and jerry's
if you look at the base flavors of their
ice creams it's predominantly vanilla
now
so
if they can do it then you can do it at
home you don't have to go for a super
fancy flavoured ice cream base it can
just be vanilla
so
custard base like i mentioned in the
video earlier add the egg yolks first
ignore this tempering the egg yolks
thing that is a historic method that is
stuck in the dark ages you don't need to
do that add your egg yolks first when
your dairy is cold get it really nicely
mixed up and heat the whole thing up
together
and you will see many times over i do
that you don't get any of that scrambled
egg that
if you're unsure of how to do the egg
tempering will often result
you don't need any you don't have any of
those issues you just don't you can
stand there stir your ice cream base let
it come up to temperature when it's
ready take it off the heat pour it out
done you'll have no egg pieces in there
so
if you really want to make the best
vanilla ice cream this one is going to
be right up there with the with the best
of them so give it a bash let me know
what you think
anyway thanks very much for watching
don't forget to like and subscribe and
we'll see you next week
[Music]
you